[music]
All churches have a [music] connection
with the afterlife and a hint of what
may become of us when we shuffle off
this mortal coil. But few places of
worship make the link between religion
and death quite so apparent as the
Cemetery Church of All Saints in
Sedlick, which is a suburb of Kohora
right in the center of the Czech
Republic. The chapel, also known as the
Costnikica Osior Bine House, [music] is
decorated with the bones of an estimated
40,000 human skeletons. The bones have
been arranged in all sorts of forms and
furnishings. The vaults are framed by
great garlands of human skulls. There is
a chandelier that is said to contain at
least one [music] example of every
single bone in the human body. There are
coats of arms, literally.
How did this come about? It may look as
if it's the legacy of some bloodthirsty
medieval count, a momento left behind
[music] by Vlad the Impaler or his ilk,
but the truth is a simple case of
overcrowding.
After a 13th century [music] abbott
returned from the Holy Land with soil
from Goltha, which he sprinkled over the
cemetery, the site became the [music]
most desirable graveyard around. Many
skeletons were exumed to make room, and
the resulting pile of bones was
eventually put to ornamental use by the
monks. Today, Sedlick has [music] turned
its most infamous place into a tourist
destination. It even has a gift shop so
that those of a Macabra bent can bone up
on a little history [music] themselves.
875 South Bundy Drive, Brentwood, Los
Angeles. This was the home where on the
12th of June, 1994, Nicole Bran Simpson
was found murdered along with her
[music] friend Ronald Goldman. Goldman
was on a visit to return Nicole's
mother's sunglasses, which had been left
in the restaurant where he worked.
Nicole's ex-husband, football legend,
sports commentator, and sometime movie
star Oronthal James Simpson, known to
the world as OJ, was arrested and tried
for the two murders. But not before a
slow speed police chase of Simpson on
[music] Interstate 405 following his
failure to turn himself in and the
release of a letter he wrote to the
media denying involvement in the crimes,
but suggesting he was considering
suicide. 4 days after the chase, Simpson
appeared in court for his arraignment
and pleaded not guilty to the two
murders. The following trial lasted for
9 months and attracted so much global
[music] publicity that it was dubbed the
trial of the century.
The court case made many of the people
involved in it familiar figures. The
judge Lance Itto found himself the
subject of television [music] comedy
parodies. Prosecutor Marsha Clark and
leading member of the defense team
Johnny Cochran also found themselves in
the spotlight. Although there was a
great deal of DNA evidence against
Simpson, in the end, it seemed as if the
prosecution's case rested on its
ill-advised choice of having Simpson try
on one of the blood soaked gloves
implicated in the murders. Perhaps it
had shrunk [music] due to the blood or
following a freezing and thoring
process.
Perhaps it is true that Simpson had
stopped taking arthritis medication,
resulting in a swelling of his joints.
Or maybe he simply wasn't guilty.
Whatever the reason, the glove clearly
did not fit, and the jury took only 3
hours of deliberation before acquitting
him on both charges. Amidst talk of a
racially charged issue, mishandling by
the prosecution, and a stunned reaction
from relatives of the murder victims,
Simpson walked away, a free man.
>> As to [music] count one, is this your
verdict?
>> Any reaction? No comments. However, in
February 1997, the case took an even
more bizarre turn when a civil jury in
Santa Monica found Simpson guilty of the
wrongful death of Goldman, as well as
battery against both Goldman and Nicole
Simpson. And the file is still not
closed. A body of evidence now suggests
Simpson's son, Jason, from his first
marriage, was the real murderer. He was
24 at the time of [music] the murders
and had a history of ragefilled
psychotic episodes. And controversy
flared again when Simpson attempted to
publish a book called If I Did It in
2006. Another twist in the long and tor
drama surrounding the murders at South
Bundy Drive.
In 1936, Germany's Reich Air Ministry
paid the town of Vulgast [music] 750,000
Reichs marks for the exclusive use of a
large area of land near the mouth
[music] of the Pina River on the Baltic
coast. 2 years later it had nearly
completed a facility which included an
army research center and a lufafa test
site. The heasuktella pinamunda
abbreviated as HVP became one of five
military proving grounds and [music] the
site for the development of several
world war II guided missiles. The most
notorious was the world's first
operational liquid fuel rocket the V2
known to its designers [music] as the
A4.
The V2 rocket was the progenitor of all
modern rockets and a direct forerunner
of the Saturn 5 moon rocket. It was the
first ballistic missile and the first
man-made object launched into space. It
also took an extraordinary amount of
testing to get right. When finally used
against the Allies in World War II, V2
rockets [music] were responsible for the
deaths of around 7,000 people. But
20,000 had died during construction of
them. Most of those were slave labor
workers from the Middle Bodora
concentration camp.
As Roy Ions pointed out in his book
Hitler's terror weapons, however, by
1943 the Germans were doing [music] so
badly in the war that Hitler was
determined to press on with testing the
weapon in order to [music] build German
morale and show his troops the war was
still winnable. But still the testing
gave [music] rise to embarrassments and
mistakes. In April 1943, the commander
of the SS, Hinrich Himmler, came to
Pinamunda with the intention of taking
control of the research and development
program in order [music] to expand his
power base.
But before he could indulge in the
inevitable power play with the leaders
of the program, Walter Dornberger and
Veron Brown, a faulty test saw one of
the rockets land on Himler's own plane,
and it was back to the drawing board for
the rocket once again.
From the original missile design to the
day the V2s were finally put into
production, 65,000 changes were made. In
August 1943, the Allied forces bombed
Pinamunda, causing disruption and the
loss of several months of development.
The main production of V2s was moved to
the underground Middle Factory near
Nordhousen. War shortages also had an
effect. Testing had begun in March 1942,
but unexplained inflight disintegrations
resulted in an 80% failure rate.
There was a veritable litany of errors,
such as rockets exploding at liftoff,
noses breaking off, and steam generators
misbehaving.
But still, the Germans persevered,
realizing that if [music] they could get
the V2 to work, its supersonic and
therefore silent flight would make it a
formidable weapon. One that, unlike its
predecessor, the V1 flying bomb or the
Doodlebug, would give no warning to
unsuspecting targets.
And on the 3rd of October [music]
1942, they finally got it right with the
V2's first successful flight.
Just over 6,000 V2s were built and as
many as 3,225
were launched against Allied territory
beginning in September 1944 with attacks
on the recently liberated Paris. Other
targets [music] included Belgium,
England, and the Netherlands, with
Antworp and London being the hardest
hit. Around [music] 2,700 civilians were
killed in London, with the last British
civilian to die being 34year-old [music]
Mrs. Ivy Millichamp at a home in
Orington.
Despite this, overall, the V2 lacked
effectiveness. Its guidance systems
weren't sophisticated enough. At $2
billion US, the program was extremely
[music] expensive and basically it all
came too late. What the program did do
though was to lay the foundations
[music] for the space race that would
take off only a few short years later.
At just after 7:00 on the evening of the
21st of December 1988, a bomb exploded
[music] on Panama Flight 103, a Boeing
named Clipperade of the Sea. The
airplane had taken off from Heathrow
Airport and was on route for JFK in New
York. But the 450 g of plastic explosive
detonated in the forward cargo hold,
completely destroying the plane. Victims
and debris were scattered over a huge
stretch of southwest Scotland with both
wings and some of the fuselage landing
on Sherwood Cresant in the small town of
Locker.
Everyone on board was killed as well as
11 people on the ground. In 2001, Libyan
intelligence officer Abdel Basset Ali
MME al-Magrai was jailed for life for
the planting of the bomb, although he
has always claimed his innocence.
In a city full of recognizable
landmarks, the Tower of London still
stands out as one of the most historical
and fascinating buildings in the English
capital.
Situated on the north bank of the river
tempames, not far from Tower Bridge, its
full title is Her Majesty's Royal Palace
and Fortress, the Tower of London.
The most familiar part of the building
is the original white tower, the square
fortress, constructed by William the
Conqueror in 1078.
Today, the tower is first and foremost a
tourist destination. Famous for its yman
warders or beefeeders. They have
patrolled the grounds since 1485 when
first installed as [music] Henry VIIth's
bodyguards. Now, while they officially
protect the crown jewels, they mostly
serve as guides to [music] the thousands
of tourists who visit the tower every
year. In 2007, the first ever female
beefeater, Moira Cameron, [music] joined
their ranks.
But the tower wasn't always such a jolly
place to be. On the contrary, it has a
long and often macabra history. Its
original use was as a fortress, palace,
and prison, particularly for
high-profile or religious captives. The
tower was used as a residence by such
monarchs as Richard the Lionheart, Henry
III, and Edward I. It was Henry who made
it a significant royal palace and
constructed palatial buildings inside
the inner Bailey. It remained a royal
dwelling until the time of Oliver
Cromwell in the 1650s.
Its most infamous use, however, was as a
prison and place of torture and
execution.
The roll call of those beheaded in its
grounds includes two wives of Henry
VIII, Katherine Howard and Amberlin. The
latter's ghost is said to walk around
the tower with her head tucked
underneath her arm.
Other famous captives included Sir
Walter Raleigh, Guyforks, and even Queen
Elizabeth I, who was held for a couple
of months in 1554 on suspicion of being
involved in Wyatt's rebellion.
The tower also housed an armory and
torture chambers, which boasted such
charming implements as the scavenger's
daughter, a sort of compression
instrument, and the Duke of Exit's
Daughter, or more simply, the rack.
And while they may not have been
acquainted with either of these two
horrific daughters, the princes in the
tower [music] almost certainly suffered
within its walls. Placed there by their
uncle Richard III, the two young sons of
Edward IV were declared illegitimate by
an act of Parliament and then simply
never heard of again. Many presumed them
to have been murdered on Richard's
orders, but it seems now the truth will
never be known.
Another famous murder victim was Henry V
6th of England. Imprisoned in the tower,
he was found dead in May 1471.
Richard Duke of Gloucester has long been
suspected of the dastardly deed.
The tower was also home to a managerie
established in the [music] 13th century
and boasting a number of big cats such
as leopards and lions. The managerie
lasted until 1835 when the last of the
animals were transferred to London Zoo
in Regent's Park. The only animals left
are the famous ravens. The legend has it
that the tower, the monarchy, and the
[music] entire kingdom would fall if
they ever left. No wonder then that one
of the bee feeders's most serious duties
today is to make sure that those birds
are extremely well looked after.
Does the name Bucks Row mean anything to
you? How about the name of the person
most commonly associated with it, Jack
the Ripper? This is White Chapel, the
area in the east end of London where a
number of women [music] working as
prostitutes were mutilated and murdered
in the latter half of 1888. To this day,
there remains much debate about not only
who Jack the Ripper really was, but
which of the women in the White Chapel
murders were actually his victims. Out
of the 11 [music] or so bodies, though,
there is a group called the Canonical 5.
Mary Anne Nichols, nicknamed Polly, was
the first of these, killed on the 31st
of August, 1888. Her body was discovered
in the early hours of the morning on
Bucks Row. Bucks Row, which has since
been renamed Derwood Street, was a back
alley in White Chapel, a couple of
hundred meters away from the London
Hospital.
Some of the original buildings and brick
work still exist today, including the
low brick wall stretching east from the
board school where Pauliey's body was
found. For those of a strong
disposition, you can still trace the
Ripper steps today with various guided
tours and excursions around the sites of
the murders.
Number two of the Canonical 5 was
[music] Annie Chapman, who also had a
nickname, Dark Annie. She was found on
the 8th of September dead in a backyard
in Spittlefields with her uterus
removed. Throughout the police [music]
investigation, a huge number of letters
were sent to the police. Most of them
were declared hoaxes, but there were a
handful that the police took more
seriously. The first of these was the
dear boss letter received on the 29th of
[music] September. It was the first time
the serial killer signed himself Jack
the Ripper and also referred to clipping
a lady's ears off which rang alarm bells
the very next day.
The 30th of September was the day that
became known as the double event because
within the space of 24 hours two
mutilated bodies were discovered by
police.
Victim number three was Elizabeth
Stride, also known as Long Liz. [music]
The Swedishborn 43-year-old was found in
the early hours in Dutfield's yard off
Burner Street. [music] Like Bucks Row,
Burner Street was also renamed to play
down the ghoulish connotations.
Katherine Edos was a bit different. Her
body was [music] found outside of White
Chapel in Miter Square in the city of
London. This was the furthest west
[music] of all the murders. And the fact
that she was found on the same day as
Elizabeth Stride has made some
ripperologists, as those who study the
case are called, claim her murder as
proof that there wasn't just one ripper,
but at least two killers at large at the
same time. [music]
It [music] was Edos's corpse, however,
that persuaded the police that the dear
boss letter was probably genuine.
As well as missing a uterus and a
kidney, she was found with [music] one
ear severed. It was this kind of
mutilation that led people to suspect
that the killer may be a surgeon or a
butcher. The next missive attributed to
the killer was the saucy Jack postcard
which was delivered on the 1st of
October and referred to both ear removal
and the so-called double event of the
previous day. Those details were already
known by journalists, however, and so
the car [music] could still have been a
hoax.
With such widespread publicity and
reporting of the murders, citizens
[music] were understandably nervous. and
one of them, George Lusk, led the White
Chapel Vigilance Committee to patrol the
streets at night. It was to Lusk that
the next letter was addressed. It is
widely thought to be the most probably
authentic epistle, largely because it
arrived accompanied by a box containing
half a human kidney preserved in
alcohol. The writer made a gruesome
claim about the other half. I fried and
ate it, the letter said. It was very
nice.
The last of the canonical five was Mary
Jane Kelly, nicknamed Ginger. She was
the only one of them found indoors,
discovered on the bed in her single room
at Miller's Court in Spittlefields.
Her corpse was the most mutilated so
far, with her heart being completely
removed and many other internal organs
taken out of her body and left around
the room. Even with contemporary
technology, we are still no closer to
solving the mystery, and the list of
possible suspects seems only to grow as
the years go by. Will we ever know the
truth?
Fidel Castro came to [music] power in
Cuba in 1959, having led the revolution
which overthrew the dictator Batista.
Castro's [music] close ties with the
Soviet Union made the United States very
nervous.
Following covert attempts to [music]
topple Castro, an economic embargo and
the failure of the USbacked Bay of Pigs
invasion by Cuban exiles in April 1961.
This mistrust and unease led to a
terrifying [music] standoff later that
year. It became known to the Russians as
the Caribbean crisis, to the Cubans as
the October crisis, and to the US and
its allies as [music] the Cuban Missile
Crisis, the closest the world has ever
come to nuclear war. Tensions rose when
the United [music] States deployed 15
Jupiter nuclear missiles in Turkey. A
Jupiter's range of 1500 mant
threat to Moscow. The Russians reacted
immediately and US reconnaissance planes
sent [music] out on the 14th of October
spotted missile launching sites being
constructed in Cuba. The incriminating
photographs were shown to the new
President John F. Kennedy who had
succeeded Eisenhower [music] in January.
The escalating crisis soon became a
baptism of fire for the 44year-old
president. Kennedy called a meeting of
the [music] executive committee of the
National Security Council
>> to halt this offensive buildup. A strict
quarantine on all offensive military
equipment under shipment to Cuba is
being initiated.
All ships of any kind bound to Cuba from
whatever nation or port where they're
found to contain cargos of offensive
weapons be turned back.
>> Assuing a surgical air strike and
resisting pressure from the joint chiefs
of staff for an all-out invasion,
Kennedy decided that the best course of
action was a naval blockade of Cuba.
Although for reasons of international
law, the term quarantine was used
instead of blockade. Over the next few
days, the Russians via diplomat Andre
GMO continued [music] to deny the
presence of any missiles in Cuba. But
the U2 reconnaissance planes reported
that four Cuban sites were not only
built, but fully operational.
The Soviet Union's president, Nikita
Kruef, labeled the quarantine an act of
aggression. And amidst no letup in the
work on the missile sites, the Cubans
prepared [music] themselves for a US
invasion.
By the 25th of October, the crisis was
at a head with the US at defense
readiness condition defcon 2 for the
first time in history and the Soviets
showing no signs of backing down.
By the 27th of October, Castro was ready
to fight, and he drafted a letter to
Kruev calling for a preemptive strike on
the United [music] States. He also
issued a directive that all Cuban
anti-aircraft weapons should fire on any
[music] US aircraft. Previously, that
order was only for groups of two or more
aircraft. Kruef, however, remained calm
and the next morning he broadcast a
message on Radio Moscow, offering a new
solution to the crisis.
Kruef promised to remove the Cuban
missiles if the Americans agreed to
remove the Jupiters from Turkey, despite
Turkeykey's continued insistence that
they wanted the missiles to stay. During
the next meeting, President Kennedy
pushed for an agreement to Kushchev's
proposal, but his advisers were against
it as they thought it would undermine
NATO and Turkey.
Around midday on the 27th, a US Lockheed
U2 plane was shot down in Cuba, adding
to the tension. But Kennedy, despite
earlier promising to launch an attack if
that happened, held tight.
By the end of the day, the US had
drafted a letter to the USSR suggesting
that they remove the weapons system from
Cuba in exchange for the US removing the
naval quarantine and promising not to
invade Cuba. No mention was made of
Turkey, but there was an unofficial
agreement that the weapons in Turkey
would be voluntarily dismantled after
the standoff was resolved. The Americans
didn't really expect a positive response
to their message. But after the
intervention of the United Nations, at
9:00 [music] a.m. on the 28th of
October, Kruef aired another broadcast
on Radio Moscow, agreeing to dismantle
the Cuban missiles and return them to
the Soviet Union. The crisis was over.
Although many believed that the result
was a compromise. But considering how
close the world got to allout nuclear
war, a few bruised egos were a very
small price to pay indeed.
3 2 1
>> [music]
[music]
>> One of the most successful thefts in
British history was the so-called great
train robbery. On the 8th of August
1963, a gang of about 15 men held up the
traveling post office [music] train on
route from Glasgow to London. Tampering
with the signals at Sears Crossing,
[music] the robbers then took the
uncoupled money train to Bridego Railway
Bridge at Leadburn in Buckinghamshire.
There they stole around 2.6 million,
[music] the equivalent of about 40
million in today's money, and over 8
times the amount usually carried on the
train due to a Scottish [music] bank
holiday.
The gang had no guns. a fact which
accounts for the response to them from
the British public. By some, the robbers
were regarded almost affectionately, but
the crime was not really a victimless
one. The co-driver, David Whitby, was
thrown down a railway embankment, and
the driver, Jack Mills, was abducted
before being hit over the head with an
iron bar, causing trauma headaches for
the rest of his life. An anonymous tip
off led to the arrests and imprisonment
of 13 members of the gang. The most
famous [music] Ronny Biggs escaped after
15 months and lived for many years in
Australia and Brazil before returning
home to England in 2001 at the age of
71. Citing increasing ill health and
mounting medical bills in Brazil, he was
sent back to jail with 28 years of his
sentence [music] remaining. In July
2007, he was moved to Norwich prison on
compassionate grounds.
This is the IMLA racetrack in Italy. In
2004, around 1,000 fans gathered there
to mark the 10-year [music] anniversary
of the death of their hero, 34year-old
Brazilian racing driver, Eton [music]
Senna Dilva. Even today, Senna is
considered by some to be the greatest
Formula 1 racing driver of all time. His
achievements in the sport were
outstanding. He won the World
Championship three times and scored 65
pole positions in 162 races. He won the
Monaco Grand Prix six times, [music]
five times consecutively between 1989
and 1993. This record still stands.
Having parted company from the McLaren
racing team in [music] 1993. On the 1st
of May of the following year, Senna
lined up for his third race with the
Williams Renault team at IMLA. And as
was so often the case, he began [music]
the race in pole position. But seven
laps into the 1994 San Marino Grand
Prix, Senna's vehicle broke [music]
traction twice at the rear, left the
track at Tambberell Corner, and slammed
into a concrete barrier at 218 km/ hour.
Despite losing a wheel and the nose
cone, the car [music] didn't seem to
have sustained much damage. But it soon
became apparent that Senna's helmet was
punctured at the top of the visor. It is
thought that the tire and the attached
piece of suspension had hit him, causing
a fatal cranial trauma. His death was
even more poignant, coming only one day
after a crash had claimed the life of
Austrian driver Roland Ratzenberger in
practice at the same event. Senna had
been greatly affected by Ratzenberger's
death, which reinforced safety fears
that already concerned him. He insisted
on visiting the crash site to see what
went wrong. And when his car was
examined following his accident the next
day, a blood soaked Austrian flag was
found inside. He had been intending to
raise it as his victory flag in honor of
Ratzenberger.
As the news of his death spread, the
Brazilian government [music] declared 3
days of national mourning and he was
given a state funeral. It was the first
death in a Formula 1 event for 12 years.
And controversy surrounded the tragedy
when it was suggested that in the two
separate accidents, both he and
Ratzenberger had died immediately, but
had been kept on life support until away
from the track so that the event
wouldn't be abandoned in line with
racing laws. More controversy loomed
over the roadworthiness of the car
itself, and for many years, the Williams
[music] team fought a manslaughter
charge through the Italian courts. They
were eventually found not guilty.
Senna's driving prowess wasn't his only
legacy, however. After his death, it was
revealed that he had donated millions of
dollars to children's charities [music]
and founded an institution to help the
disadvantaged, which is still thriving
today.
For over 30 years, [music] the TSMS
Laconia had a varied and successful
history as a passenger liner, troop
carrier, and cruise ship. On the 22nd of
December, 1963, [music]
she was 550 mi northwest of Casablanca
and 3 days into an 11-day Christmas
cruise. [music]
At about 11 p.m., a fire caused by
faulty wiring started in the ship's
hairdressing salon. It spread rapidly,
but the order to abandon ship wasn't
given until a couple of hours later,
and despite the ship [music] passing a
safety inspection 24 hours before
setting sail, there were serious safety
issues overlooked.
Many of the lifeboats were unusable due
to rusted chains and lockers [music]
containing life-saving equipment could
not be opened.
Other lifeboats burned [music] before
they could be launched. And one survivor
later complained that the fire alarm was
so weak it sounded like someone ringing
a waiter for tea.
Though many survivors were picked up,
there was still a heavy loss of life.
Out of the 1,022 people on board, a
total of 128 died. [music]
A couple of days later, some tugboats
began towing the [music] badly damaged
ship to Gibralta. But on the 29th of
December, she rolled over and sank in
only [music] 3 minutes.
Clifton House, the Buckinghamshire
mansion that in its time has been home
to [music] the Aster family and various
Dukes, but really earned its infamy in
the early 60s when it became known as
the place where cabinet [music] minister
John Proffumo met topless showgirl
Christine Keeler. There's nothing the
great British public and the not so
great British media like better than a
sex [music] scandal, a spy scandal, or a
political one. But when you get all
three together, that's the best [music]
thing of all. And to this day, the
Profumo affair is the one that people
still talk about. Profumo met Keeler at
a party organized by the society
osteopath Steven Ward and had a brief
affair with her [music] despite being
married to actress Valerie Hobson.
Keeler was at the time close [music]
friends with Mandy Rice Davis, whose
vervacity and ready wit brought an even
greater spotlight on the affair. The
scandal really developed when news of
the affair spread. Coupled with the
revelation that Keeler was also seeing
Yvi [music] Ivanov, a naval attache at
the Soviet embassy.
Considering Britain was in the middle of
the Cold War, the security breach
implications of this led to questions in
[music] the House of Commons with
Profumo compounding his disgrace by at
first lying about the affair, saying
there had been no impropriety
whatsoever. When Prerumo was [music]
finally forced to admit the truth, his
position became untenable and he
resigned from the cabinet on the 5th of
June 1963.
The ripple effect spread to Prime
Minister Harold McMillan [music] who
stepped down in October with
deteriorating health. Steven Ward was
charged with living on the immoral
earnings of prostitution and committed
suicide in August. [music] While
Christine Keeler was sentenced to 9
months in prison on unrelated perjury
charges concerning another boyfriend,
Alawishas Gordon known as Lucky. [music]
Keeler kept a fairly low profile during
the whole perfumeo affair. Although she
did pose for photographer Louisis Moley.
The resulting [music] shot remains one
of the most iconic British images of the
1960s. In 2001, she published her
autobiography, The Truth at Last. Trump
Perfumo, [music] having kept a promise
never to talk about the scandal again,
died in 2006, having finally restored
his reputation after [music] many years
of charity work.
Mandy Rice Davis, on the other hand, had
plenty to say for [music] herself. She
was called to give evidence at Steven
Ward's trial and when the prosecution
remarked that Lord Astra [music] denied
any knowledge or relationship with her,
she replied, "Well, he would, wouldn't
he?" The quote has since entered popular
usage, especially amongst British
politicians. In fact, it was probably
Rice Davis who came out of the whole
Profumo scandal the best. She traded on
her notoriety, married a businessman
from Israel, and went on to open a
number of successful nightclubs and
restaurants in Tel Aviv. She also
released records and worked as [music]
an actress, even appearing in an episode
of Absolutely Fabulous in 1994.
Brixton 1985, Toxith 1981, Notting Hill
1958.
The list of race riots in the UK is a
long and englorious one, but some are
more memorable than others. The events
of August and September [music] 1958 in
Notting Hill certainly stand out. But
not quite so well remembered is that
there was also trouble in the Midland
city of Nottingham.
It all seemed to begin on [music] the
23rd of August in a pub in St. An's well
road and is believed to have been
sparked by outrage over interracial
relationships, black men and white
women.
The roots [music] of the tension were
clearly much deeper than that, though,
stretching back to the end of the
postwar economic [music] highs that had
brought Caribbean immigrants to Britain
in the first place. Dubbed by some the
Teddy Boy riots after the visible
presence of that particular
working-class male subculture, the riots
resulted in many stabbings and
resurfaced [music] a week later. This
time though, the largely white crowd
turned on itself, leading to a brawl and
many arrests.
Meanwhile, events in Notting Hill
[music] in West London were focusing
attention further south.
Apparently triggered [music] by an
attack on a white Swedish woman married
to a West Indian man. The riots and
disturbances carried on for several
nights.
Over 140 people were arrested and nine
white men convicted of serious assault
received 4-year prison sentences in what
became known as exemplary sentencing.
Harsh punishment intended [music] to act
as a deterrent.
Six years later, Claudia [music] Jones
started the now world famous Notting
Hill Carnival as a response to the
unrest and an attempt to improve the
state of race relations in Britain.
Nobody really knows why the maneating
lines of behaved the way they did,
although there are plenty of theories.
Despite their appearances, these big
cats were not lionesses, but male lions
without manes. [music]
And some think that it was their
unusually high levels of testosterone
that both diminished their hair and
considerably raised their levels of
aggression. [music] The lions were also
much bigger than normal. Theo beasts
were reckoned to weigh 500 lb and were
10 ft long. They also both had abscesses
under their teeth, leading scientists to
conclude that they were simply in too
much pain to hunt and eat tougher prey.
>> [music]
>> Or were the events of the late 19th
century simply explained by an outbreak
[music] of render pest disease, a cattle
plague which had wiped out much of the
lion's usual prey?
Local legends [music] are more fanciful.
However, it is believed by many that the
lions were summoned by African shamans
who didn't want the iron snake of the
railway encroaching on their land.
[music]
Whatever the reason, the two Saravo
maneaters were able to terrorize
Lieutenant Colonel John Henry Patterson
[music] and his men as they attempted to
build a bridge as part of the Uganda
Railway over Saravo River in Kenya from
March 1898.
Patterson only kept detailed records of
the deaths of his skilled workers, not
the indigenous Africans. So, exact
figures have been disputed.
[music] But by December of that year,
around 135 workers had been dragged out
[music] of their tents and eaten.
Patterson did everything he could to try
and hunt down the animals, finally
shooting the first lion on the 8th of
December. The second was killed [music]
3 weeks later. And as recently as 2000,
museum staff at the Chicago Field Museum
[music] of Natural History came up with
another theory to explain the lion's
abnormal hunger for human flesh. They
suggested that the lions had scavenged
the graves of inadequately buried dead
railway workers and moved from that to
live sleeping people.
Patterson's journals confirmed that
burial mans had been disturbed and
bodies eaten.
Whatever the truth, the man-eating lines
of have now taken on legendary status,
leading to their appearance in books and
such movies as The Ghost in the
Darkness, starring Michael Douglas and
Val Kilmer as Patterson.
Of
all the tragedies that have taken place
in sporting arenas, one of the most
ignoram minions would have to be the
Heisle stadium disaster of the 29th of
May 1985.
This is for the simple reason that it
was triggered not by an accident or an
act of God, but by hooliganism. The
occasion was the final of the European
Cup. England's powerhouse team Liverpool
Football Club were to play the top
Italian team Juventus at the aging
Heisle Stadium in Brussels. With around
60,000 fans in attendance, the ground
had been cordoned off to keep the fans
of the opposing team separate. One
section, however, had been reserved for
neutral supporters and with the tickets
acquired by travel agents and touts.
This resulted in a number of Juventus
fans finding themselves in close
proximity to their sworn enemies. With
just a flimsy fence dividing them, the
Liverpool supporters rushed the barrier
an hour before kickoff. As the Juventus
supporters scrambled to get away, they
[music] backed into a crumbling wall
which collapsed, killing 39 people and
injuring hundreds more. There is
confusion about whether the organizers
and players knew exactly what [music]
had happened, but it was decided to
continue with the game anyway to prevent
further disturbances. Juventus won 1-0
thanks to a penalty by Michelle Platini.
After the match, policing and stadium
concerns were ignored with Liverpool
receiving all the blame. The club was
banned indefinitely from European
competition, as were all other English
clubs. The ban [music] lasted for 5
years.
This is the capital city of the Republic
of Macedonia, which sits on the Vara
River. In 1963, while it was still part
of President Tito's socialist Federal
Republic of Yugoslavia, the city was
hit, not for the first time, by a
massive earthquake.
It had already been nearly wiped out in
[music] 518 AD and again at the end of
the 11th century. This time, the first
tremor was felt at 5:00 a.m. on the
morning of the 26th of July. It measured
6.1 on the RTER scale and killed more
than 1,000 [music] people. 80% of the
city was destroyed and 120,000 citizens
lost their homes. At the time, the
population was only around 200,000 in
total. Rescue teams from across
Yugoslavia were swiftly mobilized and a
significant international relief fund
meant that the city was quickly rebuilt.
But many historical and cultural
monuments were lost forever, as were
elements of the city's Ottoman heritage.
Today, next to a museum, the ruins of
the old train station still stand,
turned into a memorial for those that
lost their lives in the quake.
Saddam [music] Hussein was by no means
the first despot in Iraqi history.
Baghdad's military past features a long
line of dictators, [music] coups, and
counter coups. One of the bloodiest took
place on the 8th of February 1963. It
was a [music] coup d'etat orchestrated
by the baist party which included Saddam
to topple President Abdul [music] Karim
Kasim. In the fighting 5,000 Iraqis were
killed with the Ba'ists numbering their
own losses at 80.
The motivation for overthrowing Kasim
was suspected to be panarabist influence
and state control over oil. It was
carried out with the backing of the
American CIA and the British government
and resulted in a house-to-house hunt
for members of the Communist [music]
Party. Ironically, Cassim himself had
come to power only 5 years earlier in
another coup. On the 14th of July 1958,
he and his adurance had seized military
control over the Iraqi capital,
overthrowing the monarchy and executing
[music] several members of the royal
family. By 1963, he had withdrawn the
country from the pro-western [music]
Baghdad Pact, lifted the ban on the
Communist Party, and established
relationships with the Soviet Union.
Moves like seizing 98% of Iraqi land
from the Britishowned [music] Iraq
Petroleum Company served to increase
Western hostility.
The CIA [music] was so keen to see him
removed, it joined forces with a small
but militant Baist party to plot Kasim's
downfall.
[music]
Foreshadowing Saddam Hussein's own
demise 43 years later, Kasim was
executed after a show trial on the 9th
of February 1963.
The Democratic Republic of Congo, like
many other former colonies, faced a long
period of political instability and
complicated maneuverings following its
independence from its old colonizers,
Belgium, in 1960. The next 5 years
became known as the Congo Crisis with
the establishment of the first republic
ushering in a period of turmoil which
had various elements. To begin with,
there was the anti-colonial struggle
compounded by yet another displaced cold
war battle with the United States and
the Soviet Union becoming involved.
There were also successionist battles
particularly in the province of Katanga.
[music]
Katanga was one of the richest areas of
the Congo with copper, gold and uranium
[music] mines. It was led by Moyes
Shambbe who declared independence from
the rest of the country on the 11th of
July 1960. With much of these mineral
resources under the control of Belgian
industrial companies, the Belgian
[music] government supported the bid for
independence, helping the police force
to become militarized and sending
troops.
And at the center of the Katanga
fighting forces were several hundred
European mercenaries, many of them
Belgian nationals.
Eventually, the United Nations became
involved, establishing a peacekeeping
force in the area after its security
council resolution 143 of July 1960,
which asked the Belgian government to
remove its forces from the territory.
The secretary general of the United
Nations, Dag Hammershold, set up a UN
force which remained in the Congo until
1964. At its peak, it numbered nearly
20,000, but the soldiers blue helmets
were a sign that they [music] were there
to keep the peace and could only use
arms in self-defense.
The first UN troops arrived in Katang in
mid July and by September the Belgian
troops had all withdrawn but not before
Hamshold had tried to intervene
personally only to be killed in a plane
crash on route to the trouble spot.
His death came in the middle of
Operation Mora launched by the UN on the
9th of September when it became clear
that Shambbee's mercenaries were still
in control of the Jean Armory. The
operation went badly for the UN amidst
claims that it still had no official
mandate to do anything but keep the
peace.
The fighting dragged on in Katanga until
December 1962 when the UN initiated
Operation Grand Slam which proved
decisive. By 1963, the capital city
Elizabethville was under UN control and
the bid for independence was over.
When an entire country becomes
associated with an epithet like the
killing fields, it certainly warrants
inclusion in any list of infamous
places. This was the term used to
describe the mass grave sites of
Cambodia in the late 1970s. Officially
renamed as the Democratic Campuchia, the
country under the rule of the Kamir
Rouge was a very grim place indeed. The
Kir Rouge was a radical political regime
that formulated its doctrines throughout
the 1960s in Vietnamese border camps. It
believed that rural peasant farmers were
the true workingclass proletarians and
the backbone of the revolution. After a
prolonged period of increasing their
control over the rest of the country,
the Kier Rouge eventually captured the
capital nonpen on the 17th of April 1975
[music]
with Salith Sar officially becoming
prime minister in May. Salaths is better
known as Paul Pot. Once in power, Pulp
Pot could continue the doctrines that
eventually saw between 1.7 and 2 million
Cambodians exterminated out of a
population of only 7 million. Pulpot
promoted the idea of a primitivist
agrarian future. This included a radical
policy of relocation with cities emptied
and dissident forcibly re-educated or
disposed of in mass graves they [music]
were forced to dig themselves. The most
well-known of the killing fields is
Chong EC. It now houses a Buddhist
memorial to the genocide.
The Kamir Rouge was eventually brought
down following an invasion by Vietnam in
1979. The movement was not destroyed
though with Vietnam using their
resistance as an excuse to retain its
military presence in Cambodia and Kamir
Rouge representatives retaining their
seats at the United Nations. Pulpot fled
and lived in the woods [music] on the
Thai border before finally dying in
controversial circumstances on the 15th
of April 1998. He was never brought to
justice for his actions.
[music]
3 2 1
>> [music]
[music]
>> Four score and seven years ago, our
fathers brought forth on this continent
a new nation. Conceived in liberty and
dedicated to the proposition that all
men are created equal. These are the
opening lines of the Gettysburg Address,
one of the most famous and oft
delivered by President Abraham Lincoln
on the 19th of November 1863 and [music]
outlining the ethos at the heart of the
American Civil War, namely the abolition
of slavery. The speech was given 4 and
1/2 months after the clash [music] from
which it took its name, the Battle of
Gettysburg. The battle lasted for 3 days
from the 1st to the 3rd of July 1863 and
is generally regarded as the [music]
turning point of the 4-year war. The
Confederate troops of the southern
states were led by General Robert E. Lee
and having [music] recently won an
important victory at Chancellor'sville,
they were ready to resume their second
attempt at a march north, hoping to make
it as far as Harrisburg in Pennsylvania
[music]
or even Philadelphia. But first, they
had to get through a little town called
Gettysburg.
Located 8 miles to the east of South
Mountain with Marsh Creek to [music] its
southwest and Rock Creek to its
southeast, Gettysburg became a burough
in the early 1800s. By the time the
Civil War broke out, its population was
around 2,400.
As General Lee [music] reached the town,
President Lincoln urged Major General
Joseph Hooker and the Union Army to
follow closely behind. Before the battle
could commence though, Hooker was
relieved of his command, and it was
Major [music] General George Gordon
Meade and the Union's Army of the PTOAC
who resisted Lee's attacks. The
Confederates took the offensive, and on
the first day, they attacked some ridges
to the northwest of the town. The
Union's defense lines rallied, but was
swiftly overcome by two hefty
contingents of Confederate troops
orchestrated from Lee's headquarters.
The Union troops retreated, scattering
through the streets of the town. But
that was just day one. By the 2nd of
July, with most of both armies now ready
for action, me put [music] his defensive
strategy into play. More heavy
Confederate assaults triggered fierce
battles at places like Little Roundtop,
[music] the Wheatfield, Devil's Den, the
Peach Orchard, and fittingly, Cemetery
Hill. Overnight, the troops began to
count their losses before resuming their
positions the next day. Again, Lee's
forces led attacks to the east and
south, but the major skirmish was at
Cemetery Ridge, where against the advice
of the commander, Lieutenant General
James Longreet, 12,500 [music]
Confederates took part in the ill- fated
Pickicket's charge. Major General George
Picket was one of the divisional
commanders, and it was his fresh troops
who were earmarked to lead the assault.
The attack was a disaster with Union
defenses holding firm and the
Confederates sustaining terrible losses.
It was the turning point of the battle
and indeed the war with Lee forced to
abandon his invasion of the north and
make a long painful retreat to Virginia.
The final figures for the 3-day battle
made grim reading. In just 3 days, the
two armies suffered between 46,000 and
[music] 51,000 casualties with over
7,860 deaths. Although the numbers of
dead, wounded, and captured were fairly
[music] equal on both sides. It was the
Union's superior strength, nearly 94,000
men compared to [music] the Confederates
71,700,
that led to the Southerners defeat,
marking the difference between the
hand-to-h hand and artillery-led [music]
warfare of the 1800s and the allout
attacks of today with their overwhelming
so-called collateral [music] damage.
There was just one documented civilian
death during the battles. A 20-year-old
local woman called Ginnie Wade died when
a stray [music] bullet went through her
window. As the armies left Gettysburg,
the town was left with the cleanup
operation. All those corpses were left
on the ground in the hot summer sun and
had to be buried swiftly. Then there
were the 3,000 horse carcasses which
were burned to the south of the town,
resulting in such a revolting stench
that [music] some towns folk became ill.
The debris was so extensive that
Gettysburg still displayed the ravages
of the fighting 4 months later when
President Lincoln arrived to dedicate
the soldiers national cemetery and
deliver his historic address.
It ended with the memorable lines that
this nation under God shall have a new
birth of freedom and [music] that
government of the people, by the people,
for the people shall not perish from the
earth.
At about 6 on the night of the 6th of
March 1987, [music]
the unthinkable happened to the British
car ferry, the herald of free
enterprise.
Having just left the Belgian port of
Bruge Zuga for Dover in England, she was
only 90 m from shore when she capsized,
leading to the deaths of 193 passengers
and crew. The 7-year-old ferry [music]
was a roll-on rolloff craft, which meant
it had doors at both the bow and the
stern, and it soon became apparent that
through oversight and negligence, she
had left the harbor with the bow doors
still open. Only a minute and a half
into the voyage, at a speed of just
under 19 knots, water began to pour into
the car deck. This caused the ship to
list to port before writing herself and
then listing again. [music] This time,
she went right over, ending up half
submerged in the shallow water.
With the electrical systems flooded, the
ship was plunged into darkness, but a
nearby dredger saw the lights go out and
raised the alarm. Help began arriving
within half an hour, but unfortunately
the 3° C water meant that many of the
victims trapped [music] in the ship died
due to hypothermia.
It was later discovered that the crew
member responsible for shutting the
doors had gone on a break and was
asleep. Nor was the first officer on the
car deck as the ship set sail as he
[music] was trying to keep to a tight
schedule and the captain was not able to
see that the doors were still open. An
inquiry into the disaster found [music]
that there was a disease of sloppiness
throughout the towns and Torres and
company. It was also noted, however,
that fies had sailed with open doors
before without sinking. But there were
other contributing factors here to do
with the pressure created by the ship in
the shallow water, the height of the bow
doors, and the speed at which the vessel
was traveling. But even with all these
factors, disaster could still have been
averted if the ship had been divided
into watertight compartments and not
featured an open car deck. This
facilitated easy loading and unloading
of vehicles, but also meant that the
entire card deck was flooded, leading to
the ship capsizing when she turned. In
October 1987, a coroner's inquest jury
returned a verdict of unlawful killing,
and many people involved are prosecuted
for manslaughter, as was the operating
company, PNO European Ferris. And since
the accident, there have been design
improvements made to this type of ferry,
including switches on the bridge,
displaying the status of the bow doors.
Watertight ramps fitted to the bow
sections [music] and freeing flaps which
let water escape from the car deck in
case of flood. This was all too late for
the Herald [music] of Free Enterprise,
though, which was raised and made one
last voyage to India, where she was
dismantled in 1988.
Galloping Gertie was the nickname given
to the first attempt at building a
bridge to carry Washington [music] State
Route 16 across the Tacoma Narrows in
Washington State. It was open to traffic
on the 1st of July 1940 and quickly
earned its descriptive moniker for the
way it moved in the wind. As is so often
the case, the problem was one of
funding. Plans for the bridge had kicked
off in earnest in 1937 when the
Washington [music] State Tollbridge
Authority came into being and took
control of $5,000 for a feasibility
study into building a suspension bridge.
But when the authority applied to the
Public Works Administration [music] for
$1 million to build a design by local
engineer Clark Eldridge, a New York
company said they could do it for less.
The new design featured 2 1/2 m girder
supports beneath the roadway instead of
the original 7 1/2 m ones.
This decision was to prove disastrous.
And at 11:00 a.m. on the 7th of
November, just 4 months after opening,
events showed just how disastrous.
A physical phenomenon known as
mechanical resonance made the [music]
bridge swing violently from side to side
before the concrete cracked and the
bridgeg's central span plunged into the
narrows below. Amazingly, there was no
human loss of life in the incident,
although there was one death. a cocka
spaniel called Tubby who got trapped in
a car when his owner's father, local
news photographer Leonard Coatsworth,
was forced to flee for his life.
Coatsworth later received compensation
of $3640
for his car contents, including poor old
Tubby.
On the evening of Sunday the 5th of
November 1967, the 743 express [music]
commuter train was traveling from
Hastings to Chering Cross when it came
off the rails between Hither Green and
Grove Park railway stations [music]
shortly before the St. Mildred's Road
Railway Bridge in southeast London. It
was a quart 9. The [music] train was
traveling at approximately 70 mph in
heavy rain when the front wheels [music]
of the third coach hit a wedge-shaped
piece of steel that had broken away from
the track, derailing the coach. The
train continued on in this way for about
a mile, however, before the derailed
wheels hit the crossover lead of a
diamond crossing in the upfast line. The
third coach, [music] the one ahead of
it, and all the coaches behind were
affected. The coupling broke behind the
leading coach, which ran forward and
finally stopped [music] some 200 m away
from the second coach and 700 m short of
Hither Station. Of the 10 carriages that
came off the tracks, one overturned
[music] completely and another two
jacknifed under their sides.
Two of the carriages had their sides
totally ripped off. Being a Sunday
evening, the train was packed with
people traveling back into [music] the
city, and the carriages and corridors
were full. 49 people died in the
accident and nearly 80 were injured, 27
seriously. [music]
The rain and darkness meant that the
rescue workers had a particularly
difficult task, working under flood
lights to try and [music] free
survivors. Two of the more wellknown of
these were Robin Gibb of the pop group
The Beeges and Molly Hullis. Following
their narrow escape, [music] the couple
married the next year.
Poignantly, the derailment occurred only
a month before the 10-year anniversary
of the Lewisham train crash, [music]
which took place just over a mile away
and resulted in 90 fatalities.
Investigators looking into the crash
found that [music] a triangular piece of
the track had come away, leaving a gap.
It was believed that the gap had,
however, been successfully negotiated
[music] by previous trains on the busy
track.
The running off sleeper had failed
before and the replacement was a shallow
timber [music] one. It had not been well
packed. The running on rail was
supported by a concrete sleeper which
gave it very rigid support leading
[music] to severe stress on the rail as
successive trains struck it.
But the 743 had a special suspension
fitted in order to limit the sway of
bodies as there were tight [music]
clearances in the tunnels on its regular
Tumbridge Hastings route.
This caused very high wheel forces at
any [music] track irregularities, which
probably explains why this train
derailed when others didn't. [music]
It was also noted that the speed limit
on this section of the railway had been
raised from 75 to [music] 90 mph a few
months previously, and it was thought
that accordingly available resources for
basic track maintenance [music] had
simply become overwhelmed.
The accident resulted in the speeding up
of the introduction of continuous welded
rail, [music] the banning of concrete
sleepers at rail joints on the southern
region, and also the upgrading of
maintenance standards in line with the
increased wear caused by [music] faster,
heavier trains on the tracks.
For the many people who are afraid of
flying, it's what happens once the
airplane is in the air that causes them
the most apprehension. But there are
times when what happens to the plane
while it is still on the runway can be
just as deadly.
Like the horrific events of the 27th of
March 1977 at Los Rodeos airport on
Tenneref in the Canary Islands
in thick fog and following a litany of
mishaps [music] and illtimed
occurrences. Two Boeing 747s collided
with each other, killing 583 [music]
people. The accident was mostly caused
by the crew of the KM Royal Dutch
Airlines [music] Flight 4805, who were
accidentally taking off without
clearance and crashed into Pan-American
World Airways Flight 1736, which was
taxiing along the same runway. [music]
Both planes were only at the airport
because they had been diverted from Los
Palmus due to a bomb explosion.
Simultaneous radio messages canceled
each other out, and non-standard [music]
language was used between the cockpits
and the control tower. After the crash,
important changes were made to
international regulations, including
strict requirements for standard phrases
[music] and an emphasis on English as
the common working language.
Originally built in Hyde Park to
showcase the great exhibition of 1851,
[music]
the Crystal Palace was eventually moved
to a suburb of London now known as Upper
Norwood, where between 1854 and 1936,
[music]
it became a popular destination for
thousands of Victorian pleasure seekers.
After its move from Hyde Park, the huge
row iron and glass edifice wound up
being about 560 m in length and around
50 m high. It was created by Joseph
Paxton, who received a knighthood for
his efforts. For many years, the palace
was a great attraction with its
exhibitions of arts and crafts or
dinosaurs, [music] its firework
displays, balloon launches, its
fountains and trees, and grand events
such as a 3-day festival of handles
music. Queen Victoria herself called the
place enchanting.
But during the depression, diminishing
ticket sales led to poor maintenance,
and the final nail in its coffin was the
fire which ravaged the building on
[music] the night of the 30th of
November, 1936.
Around 6 p.m., the manager, Henry
Buckland, saw a red glow in a staff
lavatory. He called workmen and went
back to his duties, but within 5
minutes, the building was ablaze. 381
firefighters using 89 engines battled
the flames, but to no avail. Rumors of
arson spread, but it seems likely it was
all just [music] a tragic accident.
And just as with a smaller, earlier fire
in 1866, there wasn't sufficient
insurance to [music] cover the costs of
rebuilding. The destruction of the south
tower meant the loss of much of the
pioneering work of John Loi Bed who had
been conducting television experiments
there. The only parts left standing were
the two mighty water towers constructed
by the great Victorian engineer is
Kingdom Brunell. These two were
dismantled in the Second World War
because of fears the Germans could use
them to navigate their way to London.
And as the fire destroyed London's
favorite playground, the future Prime
Minister, [music] Winston Churchill,
pronounced, "This is the end of an age.
The world's worst offshore oil disaster
to date took place on a North Sea oil
production platform called Piper Alpha
on the 6th of July, 1988. [music] On
that date, an explosion and fire took
the lives of 167 men out of the 229 on
board at the time. The oil rig was
operated by accidental [music] petroleum
and began production 12 years before
that, drilling for oil initially and
peaking at 300,000 [music] barrels per
day, but then focusing on its new gas
recovery module from around 1980.
The conversion from oil to gas was
partly responsible for the high number
of casualties as the previous safety
[music] precautions of having the most
dangerous areas as far away from
personnel as possible were overridden
[music] with examples like the gas
compression area being situated right
next to the control room. The chain of
[music] events on the night of the 6th
of July began with maintenance work on a
pressure relief valve on one of the two
huge gas compressors. Communication
between shifts was faulty, meaning that
when compressor B failed later that
evening, operators were unaware that
compressor A should not have been
activated. The resulting explosion
destroyed the control room, which was
then abandoned. [music]
This meant that there was no one in
command able to coordinate an
evacuation.
[music] Two men dawned protective gear
and attempted to access the system
manually, but were never seen again.
As fire spread throughout the platform,
it prevented personnel from gathering at
lifeboat stations. Instead, [music] they
waited for instructions that never came
in the fireproofed accommodation block
until [music] the acrid smoke began to
filter in and escape became impossible.
Even so, the fire would have burned
itself out had it not been for the two
other platforms, Tartan and Claymore.
Lacking the authority to cease
operations, even though they could see
[music] what was happening, they
continued pumping oil through to Piper
Alpha, leading to ruptured gas lines,
further explosions, and a devastating
[music] loss of life.
Eventually, the fire was extinguished by
the renowned American firefighter Red
Adair, who [music] struggling against 80
mph winds and 25 m waves, took 3 weeks
to control the fires, pumping cement
into the wells [music] and then capping
them.
This is Abberan, a small [music] coal
mining village about 8 km south of
Murtha Tidville in South Wales. And this
was [music] the Pank Glass Junior
School. In 1966, it was led by head
mistress Anne Jennings and her 10
teachers. There were 240 pupils.
On Friday the 21st of October that year
at about 9:15 in the morning, just after
the children had finished singing All
Things Bright and Beautiful at Assembly
and were heading for their classrooms,
[music] waste tip number seven of the
local colery had collapsed, slid down
Mera Mountain, and engulfed the school,
20 houses, and a farm. The timing
couldn't have been worse. Had the
children left the assembly hall just a
few minutes [music] later, the loss of
life would have been greatly reduced as
the classrooms were on the side of the
building closest to the slag heap. At
the same time, 50 children heading for
the school by bus from nearby Mount
Pleasant were fortunately held up by
fog. This same fog initially hampered
rescue efforts considerably. But as up
to 2,000 [music] volunteers, police,
miners, and other emergency workers dug
frantically for survivors. The extent of
the tragedy [music] soon became
apparent. Only a few people were pulled
from the rubble alive, but 144 bodies
were eventually [music] recovered. 116
of them children, mostly aged between 7
and 10.
The main causes of death were found to
be esphixxia, [music]
fractured skulls, and multiple crush
injuries.
Five teachers were among the dead,
including the deputy headmaster, Mr.
Benon, who was found clutching five
children in his arms as if trying
[music] to protect them. Three of the
dead were in the farm that was hit by
the coal waste and slurry, and a
pregnant woman immediately went into
labor on hearing that her son [music]
was dead. Just over a week after the
disaster and after the last bodies had
been recovered, the Queen and Prince
[music] Philip, the Duke of Edinburgh
visited Abberan to pay their respects, a
three-year-old girl presented the Queen
with a posie on which it said, "From the
remaining children of Abberan."
Witnesses reported [music] the Queen
being close to tears.
One person who didn't hurry to visit
though was Lord Robins of Waldingham,
who at the time was chairman [music] of
the National Coal Board. He instead
decided to attend the University of
Surrey, accepting an [music] appointment
as chancellor. Robins and the NCB tried
to blame the disaster on the heavy rains
[music] that had fallen in the days
before the tragedy. But a tribunal of
inquiry thought differently. It found
the NCB to be totally responsible due to
ignorance, [music] ineptitude, and a
failure of communication. But not a
single NCB employee was sacked, demoted,
or even disciplined. The slag heap had
been built on a stream in the first
place, and its instability was known to
the mines's [music] management and the
tip workers, but nothing had been done
about it. The local Burough [music]
Council and the National Union of Miners
were both completely exonerated.
Most shocking of all, on the orders of
Harold Wilson's Labor government, part
of a massive relief fund coordinated by
the mayor and collected from all over
the world, was appropriated to make the
remaining slag heaps safe. Families
suffered the unbelievable indignity
[music] of being means tested by the
Charities Commission as to the closeness
of their relationship with their dead
child. Compensation was to be rated
[music] accordingly. The NCB tried to
pay £50 for each child but was ordered
to pay £500. In 1997, Tony Blair's new
Labor government paid back the £150,000
[music]
that had been taken from the disaster
fund. This amount ignored inflation, of
course. The adjusted figure [music]
should have been in the realm of 1.5
million. But finally in February 2007,
over 40 years after the horrific events
at Abberavan, the sum of 2 million
pounds was awarded to the village to
help local schools and to secure the
upkeep of the memorial garden and the
cemetery.
>> [music]
>> 3 2 Why?